Thomas M. Rivers Papers 1887-1963 Mss.B.R52
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1941-1963; 9.5 linear feet
  - U.S. Navy Department, Personnel Security Clearance (Box 17)
  - U.S. Navy, Orders, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - U.S., Office of Secretary of Defense, etc., Payments and Vouchers to T.M. Rivers (Box 17)
  - United States Public Health Service, The Surgeon General (Box 17)
  - The University of Chicago, Committee on Inauguration (Box 17)
  - The University of Chicago, Fiftieth Anniversary (Box 17)
  - The University of Chicago Press (Box 17)
  - University of California, Virus Laboratory (Box 17)
  - University of Cincinnati, College of Medicine (Box 17)
  - University of Kansas Medical Center (Box 17)
  - University of Maryland, Institute of Acarology (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan, Dean of Men (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan, Medical Center News Bureau (Box 17)
  - University of Oregon Medical School (Box 17)
  - University of Pennsylvania, Bicentennial Celebration (Box 17)
  - University of Pennsylvania, School of Medicine (Box 17)
  - University of Pittsburgh, Institute for Experimental Medicine (Box 17)
  - The University of Rochester (Box 17)
  - University of South Dakota, Medical Library (Box 17)
  - University of Southern California, School of Medicine (Box 17)
  - University of Texas, Postgraduate School of Medicine (Box 17)
  - University of Wisconsin (Box 17)
  - University of Wisconsin Medical School (Box 17)
  - Unknown (Box 17)
  - Upjohn Company (Box 17)
  - Valentine, Alan (Box 18)
  - van Creveld, S (Box 18)
  - Van Dyne, Joseph Roger (Box 18)
  - Van Riemsdyck Book Service (Box 18)
  - VanRiper, Hart E, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - van Rooyen, C Evan (Box 18)
  - Van Schmus, W G (Box 18)
  - Van Wesep, H B (Box 18)
  - von Magnus, Herdis (Box 18)
  - Verstraten, Giles (Box 18)
  - Vesey, D I (Box 18)
  - Veteran's Administration (Box 18)
  - Viets, Henry R (Box 18)
  - Vignoles, Mrs. A Hutton (Box 18)
  - Robert Roesler de Villiers Foundation (Box 18)
  - Vogel, Dr. and Mrs. Peter (Box 18)
  - Voice of America (Box 18)
  - Voroshilova, Marina K (Box 18)
  - Vosburgh, Charles H (Box 18)
  - Wagner, Herbert T (Box 18)
  - Wagner, Robert F (Box 18)
  - Wagreich, H (Box 18)
  - Waksman, Selman (Box 18)
  - Waldo, Paul V W (Box 18)
  - Waldorf-Astoria (Box 18)
  - Waldrop, J B (Box 18)
  - Wall, Alma G (Box 18)
  - Wall, Margaret (Box 18)
  - Wallace, G I (Box 18)
  - Walsh, William B (Box 18)
  - War Department (Box 18)
  - War Manpower Commission (Box 18)
  - Ward, Robert (Box 18)
  - Warkany, Josef (Box 18)
  - Warriner, Ruth R (Box 18)
  - Waters, Charles A (Box 18)
  - Watkins, W W (Box 18)
  - Watson, Cecil J (Box 18)
  - Watson, Thomas J (Box 18)
  - Wayne County General Hospital (Box 18)
  - Wayne County Medical Society (Box 18)
  - Wearn, Joseph T (Box 18)
  - Weaver, Harry M., 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Weaver, Warren (Box 18)
  - Webber, Jean (Box 18)
  - Webster, Leslie T (Box 18)
  - Weech, A A (Box 18)
  - Weed, Lewis H (Box 18)
  - Weinman, Howard K (Box 18)
  - Weintrop, Morris (Box 18)
  - Weiss, Paul (Box 18)
  - Weissfeiler, J (Box 18)
  - Welsch, Maurice (Box 18)
  - Welch, William Henry (Box 18)
  - Wenner, Herbert A (Box 18)
  - Wesselhoeft, Conrad (Box 18)
  - Wessman, N E (Box 18)
  - Western Reserve University, School of Medicine (Box 18)
  - Westwood, J C N (Box 18)
  - Wharton, George W (Box 18)
  - Wharton, Lawrence R (Box 18)
  - Wheat, Miss (Box 18)
  - Whipple, G H (Box 18)
  - Whitaker, Douglas (Box 18)
  - White, Goodrich C (Box 18)
  - White, J H (Box 18)
  - Whitney, Helen Hay, Foundation (Box 18)
  - Who's Important in Medicine (Box 18)
  - Who's Who in American Education (Box 18)
  - Who's Who in the Western Hemisphere (Box 18)
  - Wickman, Oscar (Box 18)
  - Wiener, Alexander S (Box 18)
  - Wigodsky, Herman S (Box 18)
  - Wilbur, Dwight L (Box 18)
  - Wilbur, Ray L (Box 18)
  - Willard Hotel (Box 18)
  - Williams, Greer (Box 18)
  - Williams and Wilkins Company (Box 18)
  - Williamsburg Restoration, Virginia (Box 18)
  - Williamsburg Savings Bank (Box 18)
  - Wilson, James L (Box 18)
  - Wilson, Marion E (Box 18)
  - Winternitz, M C (Box 18)
  - Wistar Association (Box 18)
  - Witton, Catherine J (Box 18)
  - Wolff, Harold G (Box 18)
  - Wolman, Abel (Box 18)
  - Wolverton, Charles A (Box 18)
  - Wood, Harrison F (Box 18)
  - Woodward, Frederick (Box 18)
  - Workman, W G (Box 18)
  - World Health Organization (Box 18)
  - Worthingham, Catherine (Box 18)
  - Wright, Frederick E (Box 18)
  - Wright, Jessie (Box 18)
  - Wulff, Verner J (Box 18)
  - Wylie, Harold W (Box 18)
  - Wyllie, J (Box 18)
  - Wyman, R A (Box 18)
  - X-Ray Laboratory Reports, May 1939- May 1943 (Box 18)
  - Yager, Robert H (Box 18)
  - Yaglou, C P (Box 18)
  - Yale University, School of Medicine (Box 18)
  - Yandell, Kenneth E (Box 18)
  - Yeagley, J D (Box 18)
  - Yetwin, I Jacques (Box 18)
  - Yiannari, Helene (Box 18)
  - YMCA, Naval Branch (Box 18)
  - Yoder, Dorothy Rivers (Box 18)
  - Yood, Raphael (Box 18)
  - York Avenue Redevelopment Project (Box 18)
  - Young, C C (Box 18)
  - Youmans, John B (Box 18)
  - Young, Carl (Box 18)
  - Younger, J S: Studies with Monolayer Tissue Cultures (Box 18)
  - Zangger, Blondina (Box 18)
  - Zavagli, Vittorio (Box 18)
  - Ziegler, James E (Box 18)
  - Ziegler, Newell R (Box 18)
  - Zinsser, Hans (Box 18)
  - Zuco, Carlo Marino (Box 18)
  - Zöllner, Fr (Box 18)
- Series I(a). Miscellaneous materials, 1909-1952; 0.5 linear feet
  - Emory University BS diploma, 1909
  - Legion of Merit (medal)
  - Public Health Research Institute Distinguished Service Award
  - University of Chicago DSc diploma, April 21, 1952
  - Miscellaneous 3x5 and 4x6 notecards
- Series II. Photographs, 1887-1963; 1.0 linear feet
  Formal and informal photographs of Thomas Rivers dating mostly from his service during the Second World War and after. Among these are a large series (over 100 images) from Naval Medical Research Unit, from Guam, and from occupied Japan, 1942-1946, including scenes of the atomic devastation in the Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
  Rivers also collected a small number of photographs of his colleagues at Rockefeller Institute and elsewhere, including several of Peyton Rous, Simon Flexner, Jacques Loeb, William Welch, Rufus Cole, Walter B. Cannon, along with a smaller number of photos of the Institute itself and its staff.
  - Cannon, Walter B., n.d.; 1 item (Box 1)
    Photo of painting.
  - Cole, Rufus Ivory, n.d.; 2 photos (Box 1)
    Formal portrait and portrait with baby.
  - Flexner, Simon, 2 photos (Box 1)
    Profile photo by Louise Schmidt.
  - Loeb, Jacques in laboratory at Woods Hole, Mass., July 1921; 1 photo (Box 1)
  - Nagasaki (Japan) Atomic devastation, ca.1945-1946; 33 photos (Box 1)
    Views of devastation of Nagasaki and Shimonoseki; spraying DDT; American POWs; Japanese citizens.
  - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis Medical Advisory Meeting, Hot Spring, Va., April 1949; 8 photos (Box 1)
    Candid photos at party, including Rivers and wife, Dorothy Ducas, Morris Fishbein, Charles Lowman, Basil O'Connor, James Simmons, Catherine Worthingham, Jessie Wright.
  - Nimitz, Chester W. talking with Commander Shope, Capt. Rivers, and Commander Lamar, ca.1945; 1 photo (Box 1)
  - Nimitz, Chester W. at formal surrender of Japan, U.S.S. Missouri, September 2, 1945; 1 photo (Box 1)
  - O'Connor, Basil. Signed photographs, 1947, n.d.; 3 photos (Box 1)
    Three photos inscribed from O'Connor to Rivers, including group photo of participants at the Annual Meeting of the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, Warm Springs, Ga., 1947
  - Rivers, Thomas M. (Box 1)
    - Formal portraits 1, ca.1950; 16 prints (Box 1)
      Prints of two different, 8x10" studio portraits.
    - Formal portraits 2, ca.1935-1950; 10 prints (Box 1)
    - Laboratory images, ca.1933-1950; 13 prints, 3 negatives (Box 1)
      Photographs of Rivers in hospital and lab, including views of young polio patients.
      - Thomas M. Rivers, holding test tubes.
    - Navy, ca.1944-1946; 12 prints (Box 1)
      Formal and semi-formal portraits of Rivers while in the naval service. Includes signed photo from Maj. Gen. Henry L. Larsen presenting Rivers with the Legion of Merit, 1945.
      See also NAMRU (Guam).
    - New York Worlds' Fair, 1939; 4 prints (Box 1)
      Publicity photos of reception given in the Medicine and Public Health Building for the International Congress of Microbiologists.
      Includes Arne Diselius, Louis I. Dublin, William S. Gordon, Dr. Jensen, Fiorello LaGuardia, Alfred Petterson, C. E. A. Winslow.
    - World War I, ca.1918; 9 prints (Box 1)
      Unidentified snapshots.
    - Miscellaneous informal and family photos, ca.1915-1955; 26 prints (Box 1)
      Includes several photos of Rivers and his wife.
  - Rivers, Thomas M. and Melvin A. Glasser, Westminster Abbey, ca.1950; 1 print (Box 1)
  - Rivers, Thomas M. and Fiorello LaGuardia, ca.1939; 1 print (Box 1)
  - Rivers, Thomas M., James B.Murphy and visitor, July 2, 1937; 2 negs. (Box 1)
  - Thomas M. Rivers, portrait, half-length., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal 3/4 view portrait.
  - Rockefeller Institute buildings, ca.1925-1928; 5 prints (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller Institute. First home at 127 E. 50th Street, New York, n.d.; 1 print (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller Institute. Staff, ca.1910, ca.1938; 2 prints (Box 1)
    One photo includes Simon Flexner; the later of Rockefeller Hospital staff with Rivers.
  - Rous, Peyton at dinner of the American Committee of the Weizmann Institute, November 27, 1956; 5 prints (Box 1)
    Photos of dinner, including Otto Loewi, Abba Eban, et al.
  - Rivers, Thomas M. and Fiorello LaGuardia, ca.1939; 1 print (Box 1)
  - Rous, Peyton, receiving honorary degree, Magill University, October 6, 1949; 4 prints (Box 1)
  - Rivers, Thomas M. and Fiorello LaGuardia, ca.1939; 1 print (Box 1)
  - Tissue preparation (Rivers and Ward), 1 print (Box 1)
    Figure for published paper.
  - Welch, William H., with Susan and Archie looking at rabbits being used for poliomyelitis experimental work, Charlton Hall, Irvington, Summer 1887; 1 print (Box 1)
  - Welch Centennial Dinner, Baltimore, 1950; 1 print (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified, Summer 1887; 23 prints (Box 1)
  - Naval Medical Research Unit (NAMRU) II (Guam), 1944-1946; 15 folders (Box 2)
    - Animal cages, ca.1944-1946; 3 prints (Box 2)
    - Blomquist, Lt. Commander (Chaplain), May 23, 1944; 1 print (Box 2)
    - Buildings and grounds, ca.1944-1946; 22 prints (Box 2)
    - Construction, ca.1944-1945; 6 prints (Box 2)
    - General views of base, ca.1944-1946; 39 prints (Box 2)
      Includes shots of staff playing baseball, general views of NAMRU grounds, some including Rivers.
    - Hospital, ca.1944-1946; 5 prints (Box 2)
    - Laboratories, ca.1944-1946; 47 prints (Box 2)
      Views of laboratory facilities, visitors to laboratories, etc., including a few with Rivers.
    - O'Connor, Basil. Visit to NAMRU, May 23, 1945; 6 prints (Box 2)
    - Personnel, ca.1944-1946; 14 prints (Box 2)
      Mostly informal images of workers at NAMRU, at rest and at work.
    - Rivers, Thomas M., ca.1944-1946; 18 prints (Box 2)
      Mostly informal shots of Rivers at NAMRU.
    - Rivers, Thomas M. (color transparencies), ca.1944-1946; 7 prints (Box 2)
    - Rockefeller, Winthrop, May 1945; 1 print (Box 2)
      Inscribed to Rivers.
    - Miscellaneous, ca.1944-1946; 10 prints (Box 2)
      Includes two views of Guamian natives, a wedding on base, flag raising at NAMRU.
    - Negatives, ca.1944-1946; 20 negs., 40 images (Box 2)
    - Negatives, ca.1944-1946; 9 negs., 18 images (Box 2)